Guide to the Brashear Association Records, 1891-1978 AIS.1979.17
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Papers of John Alfred Brashear, 1840-1920, 1891-1919; IX.
  Folder 75 contains Birthday Memorabilia and most of the material pertains to the 100th anniversary celebration in 1940. Included is a printed pamphlet by R. O. Hughes, newpaper and magazine articles, speeches, programs, and poems in honor of the occasion. Some material from other anniversary celebrations since Brashear's death, as well as from his birthday celebrations during his life-time.
  Folder 76 contains genealogical material in the form of correspondence and notes. Most of this material pertains to relatives of John Brashear. Persons named include Mrs. Emmett Cary and Mrs. E. J. Paulson of Pittsburgh, John A. Brashear of Mount Vernon, New York, Julia Dangerfield Glass of New Orleans, and Cecele Gruet of Brooklyn, New York.
  Folder 77 consists of unpublished biographical materials which include drafts of lectures, dittoed scripts of dramatizations, several typed biographical summaries in both outline and narrative form. Most items are unsigned and undated. Included are two lectures by James O'Brien, Executive Director of the Brashear Association which were presented for Pittsburgh's South Side Rotary Club in 1974 and for the Pittsburgh History and Landmarks Foundation's Famous Pittsburghers Bicentennial Lecture Series in 1977. Folder 79 contains an article which "gave the inspiration for the founding of the Brashear settlement." In Folder 80 the printed issue of the article by Ann M. Kendlehart is included as is a typed manuscript of the article. The Pennsylvanian, which contains an article by Helen Fendrick, was published by the Pennsylvania Historical Junto in Washington, DC.
  - General, 1.
    - Papers, 1891-1919 (Box 5, Folder 73-74)
    - Birthday Memorabilia, 1917-1953 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Genealogical Material, 1951-1978 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Unpublished Biographical Materials, 1916-1977 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Radio Broadcasts, 2.
    - Broadcasts, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 78)
      Includes:"Adventures in Research: Beloved Lens Maker" in Modern Americans in Science and Invention Series.
      "Path to the Stars" in the Cavalcade of America Series, presented by the DuPont Company on NBC, June 5, 1971.
  - Pamphlets and Articles, 3.
    - "Uncle John Brashear" in American Magazine by Merle Crowell, 1916 (Box 5, Folder 79, Item 1)
    - "Get Interested in Something: Have a Hobby--Studying the Stars is Mine" in American Magazine by John Brashear, 1916 (Box 5, Folder 79, Item 2)
    - "The Story of John Alfred Brashear: The Man Who Loved the Stars" by the Brashear Association, November 1959 (Box 5, Folder 80, Item 1)
    - "The Man Who Loved the Stars" in Carnegie Magazine by Ann M. Kendlehart, November 1959 (Box 5, Folder 80, Item 2)
    - "John Alfred Brashear" in The Pennsylvanian, Volume 18, by Helen Fendrick, March-December 1963 (Box 5, Folder 80, Item 3)
  - Books, 4.
    - Brashear, John. The Autobiography of a Man Who Loved the Stars. New York, American Society of Mechanical Engineers. 262 p. Indexed., 1924 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Gaul, Harriet and Ruby Eiseman. Scientist, Humanitarian, 1840-1920. University of Pennsylvania Press, 220 p. Indexed, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 5.
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1916-1977 (Box 5, Folder 83)
- South Side Historical Materials, X.
  Folder 84 contains the study entitled South Side Ethic Groups which resulted from the Conference on Racial and Industrial Development of the South Side. This conference took place in October, 1928 and the 1929 study contains information on the English, Irish, Polish, Welsh, Ukrainian, Czechoslovakian, Lithuanian, and African American communities in the South Side. Folder 85 contains a typed manuscript of a sketch of the South Side which includes maps and clippings. There is a signature on the flyleaf: "Frank Skalak." and the cover states: "This is the only copy available." Folder 91 contains two issues of Closer Look, a publication by the Birmingham Union for the Restoration of Pittsburgh's South Side. The June-August, 1977 issue (Volume 2, No.3) contains an article on glassmaking in the South Side. The April, 1977 issue is Volume 2, No.2. In Folder 96, the miscellaneous clippings and short mss. concern South Side history and primarily the anniversary of the [Civil] "War Scar" from June 14, 1863 and the McKinley Fort on the South Side. The miscellaneous items in Folder 97 consist of programs, posters, and ticket stubs.
  - South Side Ethnic Groups from the Conference on Racial and Industrial Development of the South Side in October, 1928, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - A Brief Sketch of the South Side compiled by the Pupils of the Eleventh Grade, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Our South Side by Bert Gold (Field Instructor, School of Applied Social Sciences, University of Pittsburgh)(2 copies), 1923 1942 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - The Georgetown of Pittsburgh, Speech to South Pittsburgh Development Council by Calvin S. Hamilton (Executive Director, Pittsburgh Department of City Planning, May 27, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Allegheny County Profile (Draft), August 1, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - South Side Survey Synopsis Report (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - History of Pittsburgh South of the Point, Prior to 1925. (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - History of the South Side (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Closer Look published by Birmingham Union for the Restoration of Pittsburgh's South Side, June-August 1977 April, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - ASI Nationality Fact Sheet and Newsletter, 1947, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Map: South Side Housing Study by the Urban Redevelopment Authority of Pittsburgh (2 xerox copies) (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Birmingham, 1763-1976 Bicentennial Booklet by Robert K. Hayden (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and short mss. (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Miscellaneous items from South High School and other South Side institutions (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Needs Assessment of the South Side: study for the Brashear Association, Pittsburgh, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Letterpress Copy Book related to Business of the Brashear Association, November 18, 1908 - April 20, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Inventory of Brashear Museum (Box 5, Folder 100)
- Oversize Material, XI.
  This material was added to the finding aid in December 2010.
  - Picture, "Seventh Conference, National Federation of Settlements-Lillian House, Kingsley Association", 1917; 1. (Map-case 7, Drawer 4)
  - Text of room dedication to Martha C. Hoyt, 2.
  - Paper with pre-litho positioning, 3.
  - Metal Litho with picture of Martha C. Hoyt's house, 4.
  - Sheet with Pan-American and unidentified dinner pictures, 5.
  - Picture, "George Washington Carver House,", 1940; 6.
  - Last known picture of Dr. John Brashear, 1920; 7.
  - Painting of John A. Brashear, by A. Benziger, 8.
  - Pictures of John A. Brashear, 1919; 9.
  - Picture of John A. Brashear, 1919; 10.
  - Titled "Folder 3", with newsclippings, 1940; 11.
  - Titled "Folder 2" with various newsclippings, 1940; 12.
  - Titled "Folder 1" with various newsclippings, 1940; 13.
  - Bag labeled, "John A. Brashear papers" VERY FRAGILE, 14.
  - Biography of Martha C. Hoyt, 15.
  - Magazine titled, "The Index", article titled, "Brashear Chats with China's President", 1917; 16.
  - Newspaper titled, "Pittsburgh Bulletin", 17.
  - Various newspaper articles, 18.
  - Scripts of radio broadcasts on John Brashear's life, 19.
  - Picture, "Closing Session, Pan-American Scientific Conference, Washington D.C.", 1916; 20.
  - Picture, "Second Pan-American Conference, Washington D.C.", 1915; 21.
  - Picture of unknown dinner, 1907; 22.